<section id="command-groupboxcreate">
    <title>GROUPBOXCREATE</title>
<indexterm><primary>GROUPBOXCREATE</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>GROUPBOXCREATE</command> <parameter>parent</parameter> <parameter>name</parameter> <parameter>xpos</parameter> <parameter>ypos</parameter> <parameter>width</parameter> <parameter>height</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Create a group box control.
A group box control is a unique control compared with the other controls because all it does is group radio buttons (see <link linkend="command-radiobuttoncreate">RADIOBUTTONCREATE</link>) and checkboxes (see <link linkend="command-checkboxcreate">CHECKBOXCREATE</link>) both graphically and logically.
Radio buttons and checkboxes must belong to a group box control.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>parent</parameter> input is the name of the window that owns the new group box control.
If no window or dialog with that name exists, then the &PRODUCTNAME; screen window is used as the parent.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>name</parameter> input identifies the new group box control and <emphasis>must</emphasis> be a unique word.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>xpos</parameter> input is the X coordinate where the upper-left corner of the new group box control is placed.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>ypos</parameter> input is the Y coordinate where the upper-left corner of the new group box control is placed.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>width</parameter> input is the width of the new group box control.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>height</parameter> input is the height of the new group box control.
</para>

<para>
If the parent of the group box is the &PRODUCTNAME; screen window, then the <parameter>xpos</parameter>, <parameter>ypos</parameter>, <parameter>width</parameter>, and <parameter>height</parameter> inputs are all given in turtle coordinates.
Otherwise, they are given in "dialog units", the origin is the upper-left corner of the parent, and Y values increase as you move down the screen.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
    <programlisting><userinput>TO CHECKONTHINGS
  IFELSE CHECKBOXGET "myhideturtle [HIDETURTLE] [SHOWTURTLE]
END

WINDOWCREATE "main "mywindow "mytitle 0 0 100 100 []
GROUPBOXCREATE "mywindow "mygroupbox 10 10 80 40
CHECKBOXCREATE "mywindow "mygroupbox "myhideturtle [Hide Turtle] 20 20 60 20
BUTTONCREATE "mywindow "mybutton "Go 40 50 25 25 [CHECKONTHINGS]</userinput>

<replaceable>Clicking on the Go button shows or hides the turtle,
depending on whether the checkbox is checked.</replaceable>

<userinput>; Delete the window and all of its child controls.
WINDOWDELETE "mywindow</userinput>
</programlisting>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</section>
