<section id="command-netconnecton">
<title>NETCONNECTON</title>
<indexterm><primary>NETCONNECTON</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>NETCONNECTON</command> <parameter>remotemachinename</parameter> <parameter>remoteport</parameter> <parameter>sendready</parameter> <parameter>receiveready</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Initiates a connection over the network to the TCP port <parameter>remoteport</parameter> on <parameter>remotemachinename</parameter>.
To turn off the connection call <link linkend="command-netconnectoff">NETCONNECTOFF</link>.
To obtain the data received call <link linkend="command-netconnectreceivevalue">NETCONNECTRECEIVEVALUE</link> in your <parameter>receiveready</parameter> instruction list.
When you actually send data with <link linkend="command-netconnectsendvalue">NETCONNECTSENDVALUE</link> it might output FALSE (meaning that it's not ready to send).
If this happens you must wait until the <parameter>sendready</parameter> callback code is run before trying to send the data again.
Note you cannot just send data from the <parameter>sendready</parameter> callback code, it won't be run unless the previous send was blocked.
</para>

<para>
NETCONNECTON outputs TRUE if the operation was successful.
Otherwise, it outputs FALSE.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>remotemachinename</parameter> input is a DNS host name or an IP address.
It can be a list or a word.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>remoteport</parameter> input is an integer that is used to identify which remote TCP port to connect to.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>sendready</parameter> input is an instruction list (a list of instructions or a procedure name) to run when data is ready to send again.
The first time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; successfully invokes the connection request.
The second time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; actually connects to the remote machine.
The third time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; is ready to send on the connection.
After that, <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run when &PRODUCTNAME; is ready to send after an earlier call to NETCONNECTSENDVALUE failed.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>receiveready</parameter> input is an instruction list (a list of instructions or a procedure name) to run when data are available.
It is run whenever data is received and is ready to be read.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<para>This example assumes that a machine named "remotemachinename" is listening on port 5124.
<programlisting><userinput>NETSTARTUP ; Start up the network
SHOW NETCONNECTON "remotemachinename 5124 [PRINT [ready to send again]] [PRINT [I have something]]</userinput>
true

<userinput>NETCONNECTOFF
NETSHUTDOWN</userinput>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</section>
