<section id="command-setturtlemode">
<title>SETTURTLEMODE</title>
<indexterm><primary>SETTURTLEMODE</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>SETTURTLEMODE</command> <parameter>mode</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Sets the bitmap mode for the currently selected turtle.
The bitmap mode controls how bitmapped turtles (see <link linkend="command-bitmapturtle">BITMAPTURTLE</link>) paste their image onto the screen.
Sometimes you want the background erased and sometimes not.
Sometimes you wish to invert the image before pasting it and sometimes not.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>mode</parameter> input must be an integer from 1 to 9.
The meaning of each value is given by the following table:

<informaltable frame='all'>
  <tgroup cols='2'>
    <thead>
      <row><entry>Mode</entry> <entry>Turtle Image</entry></row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row><entry>1</entry> <entry>The bitmap in memory, without modification</entry></row>
      <row><entry>2</entry> <entry>A bitwise OR of the bitmap in memory and the screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>3</entry> <entry>A bitwise AND of the bitmap in memory and the screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>4</entry> <entry>A bitwise XOR of the bitmap in memory with the screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>5</entry> <entry>A bitwise AND of the bitmap in memory with the bitwise inversion of screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>6</entry> <entry>A bitwise inversion of the bitmap in memory</entry></row>
      <row><entry>7</entry> <entry>A bitwise OR of the bitmap in memory with the bitwise inversion of the screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>8</entry> <entry>A bitwise OR of the bitwise inversion of the bitmap in memory and the screen</entry></row>
      <row><entry>9</entry> <entry>A bitwise inversion of the screen</entry></row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

<para>
SETTURTLEMODE has no effect if the selected turtle is not currently bitmapped.
It is an error to run SETTURTLEMODE on a turtle that was bitmapped with a rotating bitmap.
</para>

<para>
Use <link linkend="command-setturtle">SETTURTLE</link> to select a different turtle.
</para>

<para>
Use <link linkend="command-turtlemode">TURTLEMODE</link> to obtain the selected turtle's mode.
</para>

<para>
Use <link linkend="command-bitmapturtle">BITMAPTURTLE</link> to map a turtle to a bitmap.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>



<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<programlisting><userinput>; Fill the screen with white
SETSCREENCOLOR [255 255 255]
CLEARSCREEN

; Draw a circle and fill it with red
PENDOWN
CIRCLE 50
SETFLOODCOLOR [255 0 0]
FILL

; Copy the red circle to the clipboard
PENUP
SETXY -50 -50
BITCOPY 101 101

; Use a simple copy for the turtle's mode
BITMAPTURTLE

; Fill the screen with yellow
SETSCREENCOLOR [255 255 0]
; Notice that the white corners show up when using the default turtle mode

; Set the turtle mode to AND the image onto the background
SETTURTLEMODE 3
; Notice that the white corners disappeared</userinput>
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</section>
