<section id="command-ellipsearc">
<title>ELLIPSEARC</title>
<indexterm><primary>ELLIPSEARC</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>ELLIPSEARC</command> <parameter>angle</parameter> <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> <parameter>startangle</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Draws part of (or all of) an ellipse based on the turtle heading, turtle position and given inputs.
ELLIPSEARC does not move the turtle.
The center-point of the elliptic arc is the turtle's current position.
The elliptic arc starts at a location given by <parameter>startangle</parameter> and sweeps an angle equal to <parameter>angle</parameter> degrees in the clockwise direction.
</para>

<para>
The size and shape of the elliptic arc are determined by the <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> and <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> inputs.
The <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> input is the distance from the turtle to the ellipse in the direction perpendicular to the turtle's current heading.
The <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> input is the distance from the turtle to the ellipse in the direction in which the turtle is currently heading.
This implies that the turtle's heading determines the orientation of the ellipse.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>startangle</parameter> input is relative to the turtle's current heading.
A <parameter>startangle</parameter> of 0 indicates that the elliptic arc starts behind the turtle.
The <parameter>startangle</parameter> is measured in a clockwise direction, so a value of 90 indicates that the elliptic arc should start to the turtle's left (90 degrees clockwise from behind the turtle).
</para>

<para>
Normally the elliptic arc is draw clockwise, but if the <parameter>angle</parameter> input is negative, then the elliptic arc is draw counter-clockwise.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<para>
A 2D example:
<programlisting><userinput>ELLIPSEARC 360 100 200 0
CLEARSCREEN
ELLIPSEARC 90 50 50 0
CLEARSCREEN
ELLIPSEARC 90 50 50 90</userinput>
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>
A 3D example:
<programlisting><userinput>PERSPECTIVE
REPEAT 72 [ELLIPSEARC 90 100 150 45 RIGHTROLL 5]</userinput>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>See Also</term>
<listitem><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="command-ellipsearc2">ELLIPSEARC2</link></member>
</simplelist></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</section>
