<section id="command-setlabelfont">
<title>SETLABELFONT</title>
<indexterm><primary>SETLABELFONT</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>SETLABELFONT</command> <parameter>font</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Sets the font to be used by the <link linkend="command-label">LABEL</link> command.
</para>

<para>
The input is a list that completely describes a font.
The available fonts depend on your computer.
&PRODUCTNAME; has two ways to specify the font you desire.
This command can be used by &GENERICNAME; programs.
For interactive use you can use <link linkend="menu-set-labelfont">Set - Label Font</link> from the main menu.
The easiest way to use fonts in &PRODUCTNAME; is to set the desired font using the Menu and capturing the attributes using <link linkend="command-labelfont">LABELFONT</link> command.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>font</parameter> input must be a list of the form: <userinput>[[FaceName] Height Width Orientation Weight Italic Underline StrikeOut CharSet OutPrecision ClipPrecision Quality PitchAndFamily]</userinput>.
The meaning of each item within the list is explained by the following table:

<informaltable frame='all'>
  <tgroup cols='2'>
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Item</entry>
        <entry>Meaning</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>FaceName</entry>
        <entry>A word (or list of words) that is the font's typeface name</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Height</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's height, in logical units.
               If this value is greater than zero, it specifies the cell height of the font.
               If it is less than zero, it specifies the character height of the font.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Width</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's width, in logical units</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Orientation</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's orientation, in degrees</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Weight</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's weight.
               This member ranges from 0 to 900 in increments 100.
               A value of 0 means use default weight.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Italic</entry>
        <entry>An integer.  The font is italicized if and only if this is non-zero.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Underlined</entry>
        <entry>An integer.  The font is underlined if and only if this is non-zero.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>StrikeOut</entry>
        <entry>An integer.  The font is rendered with a horizontal line through it if and only if this is non-zero.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>CharSet</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's character set.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>OutPrecision</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's output precision.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>Quality</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's quality.
        0 implies the default quality (defined by the current operating system settings).
        1 implies draft quality.
        2 implies proof quality.
        3 implies no anti-aliasing.
        4 implies anti-aliasing.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>PitchAndFamily</entry>
        <entry>An integer that specifies the font's pitch and family.</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

<para>
If you choose a font typeface that is not available on the system, then SETLABELFONT lists all fonts that are available.
</para>

<para>
If you want to flash a message by writing it in one color, then writing the same message in the background color, you should disable anti-aliasing by choosing a <parameter>Quality</parameter> of 3.
Otherwise, you'll end up with a faint outline of the message you wanted to completely erase.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<programlisting><userinput>SETLABELFONT [[Times New Roman] -24 0 0 400 0 0 0 0 3 2 1 18]
LABEL "Hello</userinput>
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>See Also</term>
<listitem><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="command-fontfacenames">FONTFACENAMES</link></member>
</simplelist></listitem>
</varlistentry>



</variablelist>
</section>
