<section id="command-netaccepton">
<title>NETACCEPTON</title>
<indexterm><primary>NETACCEPTON</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>NETACCEPTON</command> <parameter>localport</parameter> <parameter>sendready</parameter> <parameter>receiveready</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Enables you to accept a connection over the network on the <parameter>localport</parameter>.
When data are available, &PRODUCTNAME; runs the <parameter>receiveready</parameter> instruction list.
To obtain the data received, run <link linkend="command-netacceptreceivevalue">NETACCEPTRECEIVEVALUE</link> in your <parameter>receiveready</parameter> instruction list.
When you send data with <link linkend="command-netacceptsendvalue">NETACCEPTSENDVALUE</link> it might output FALSE (meaning that it's not ready to send).
If this happens you must wait until &PRODUCTNAME; runs the <parameter>sendready</parameter> instruction list before trying to send the data again.
Note you cannot just send data from the <parameter>sendready</parameter> callback, it won't be run unless the previous send was blocked.
To stop accepting connections, run <link linkend="command-netacceptoff">NETACCEPTOFF</link>.
</para>

<para>
NETACCEPTON outputs TRUE if the operation was successful.
Otherwise, it outputs FALSE.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>localport</parameter> input is an integer between 1 and 65535 that is used to identify which local port to listen on.
The port must not already be in use by some other service on the machine.
It is recommended that you use ports numbers greater than 1024.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>sendready</parameter> input is an instruction list (a list of instructions or a procedure name) to run when data is ready to send again.
The first time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; successfully invokes accept.
The second time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; accepts a connection.
The third time <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run is when &PRODUCTNAME; is ready to send data.
After that, <parameter>sendready</parameter> is run when &PRODUCTNAME; is ready to send after an earlier call to NETACCEPTSENDVALUE failed.
</para>

<para>
The <parameter>receiveready</parameter> input is an instruction list (a list of instructions or a procedure name) to run when data are available.
&PRODUCTNAME; runs it whenever data is received and is ready to be read.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<programlisting><userinput>NETSTARTUP ; Start up the network

; Wait for someone to connect to you on port 5124
SHOW NETACCEPTON 5124 [PRINT [Ready to send]] [PRINT [Ready to receive]]</userinput>
true

<userinput>NETACCEPTOFF
NETSHUTDOWN</userinput>
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


</variablelist>

</section>
