<chapter id="commandline-options">
<title>Command Line Options</title>
<indexterm><primary>command line options</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Command line options can be set as properties of your shortcut to &PRODUCTNAME;.
Just add these switches after the &LOGOEXE;.
</para>

<para>
You can add any command line option to the &PRODUCTNAME; desktop shortcut so that when you double-click on it, &PRODUCTNAME; starts with the selected option.
For example, if you want to start &PRODUCTNAME; in "<link linkend="commandline-e">expert</link>" mode:


<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Right-click on the &PRODUCTNAME; desktop shortcut and select <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> from the popup menu.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Click the Shortcut tab in the Properties dialog.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
In the Target field, append "-E" so the line looks like this <userinput>"C:\Program Files\FMSLogo\fmslogo.exe" -E</userinput>.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Click the OK button.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

The next time you double-click the shortcut, &PRODUCTNAME; will start in expert mode.
</para>

<section id="commandline-w">
<title>-W</title>

<synopsis>-W <replaceable>width</replaceable></synopsis>

<para>
This sets the width of your virtual drawing workspace to <option>width</option>.
Be aware that the larger you set this the more memory is required.
The default is 1000.
</para>

<para>
If the <option>-F</option> command-line option is given in addition to <option>-W</option>, then the width of the virtual drawing workspace is reduced to fit within the dimensions of the display.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -W 2000 -H 2000</synopsis>
</section>


<section id="commandline-h">
<title>-H</title>

<synopsis>-H <replaceable>height</replaceable></synopsis>

<para>
This sets the height of your virtual drawing workspace to <option>height</option>.
Be aware that the larger you set this the more memory is required.
The default is 1000.
</para>

<para>
If the <option>-F</option> command-line option is given in addition to <option>-H</option>, then the height of the virtual drawing workspace is reduced to fit within the dimensions of the display.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -W 2000 -H 2000</synopsis>
</section>



<section id="commandline-f">
<title>-F</title>

<synopsis>-F</synopsis>

<para>
This tells &PRODUCTNAME; not to use scrollbars on the screen window ("F" stands for "fixed-size").
If this option is not given, then scrollbars are used, as needed.
If you use this option without using <link linkend="commandline-h">-H</link> or <link linkend="commandline-w">-W</link>, then &PRODUCTNAME; automatically calculates a workspace to fit your full screen.
</para>

<para>
<link linkend="command-fullscreen">FULLSCREEN</link>, <link linkend="command-splitscreen">SPLITSCREEN</link>, and <link linkend="command-textscreen">TEXTSCREEN</link> do not change the dimensions of the screen window when &PRODUCTNAME; is started in fixed-size mode.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -F</synopsis>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -F -W 400 -H 200</synopsis>
</section>



<section id="commandline-p">
<title>-P</title>

<synopsis>-P</synopsis>

<para>
This enables <link linkend="command-perspective">PERSPECTIVE</link> mode to be the default mode to start in.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -P</synopsis>
</section>


<section id="commandline-e">
<title>-E</title>

<synopsis>-E</synopsis>

<para>
This enables "Expert" mode.
</para>

<para>
In "Expert" mode the following occurs:
</para>

<para>
<link linkend="command-pos">POS</link> and <link linkend="command-posxyz">POSXYZ</link> do not "round" their output and you may see positions such as [0 -1.0e-12].
This is due to "normal" floating point errors.
Rounding POS serves no purpose other than to make the POS look good.
But in some applications this rounding can introduce errors if you save and restore the position.
In other words, SETPOS POS has no side effect (does not round) in "Expert" mode.
</para>

<para>
&PRODUCTNAME; allows multiple edit sessions.
Multiple edit sessions can lead to unexpected behavior if you don't understand how &PRODUCTNAME; manages the workspace.
If procedures are lost or have unexpected changes then you should not be using expert mode.
</para>

<para>
&PRODUCTNAME; allows you to save directly to the workspace.
Saving directly to workspace can lead to unexpected behavior if you don't understand how &PRODUCTNAME; manages the workspace.
If procedures are lost or change unexpectedly then you should not be using expert mode.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -E</synopsis>
</section>

<section id="commandline-l">
<title>-L</title>

<synopsis>-L <replaceable>file1</replaceable> <replaceable>[file2]</replaceable></synopsis>

<para>
&PRODUCTNAME; allows you to <link linkend="command-load">LOAD</link> one or more filenames on the command line when starting &PRODUCTNAME;.
These files are loaded before the interpreter starts reading commands from the commander.
If you load a file that runs a program that includes a <link linkend="command-bye">BYE</link> instruction, &PRODUCTNAME; runs that program and exits.
You can therefore write stand-alone programs in &PRODUCTNAME; and run them as new shortcuts.
Note, the "-L" switch must follow any other switches.
</para>

<para>Example:</para>
<synopsis>&LOGOEXE; -L myprog.lgo</synopsis>
</section>


<section id="invoking-and-exiting-fmslogo">
<title>Invoking and Exiting &PRODUCTNAME;</title>

<para>
To start &PRODUCTNAME;, just click on the &PRODUCTNAME; icon.
To exit &PRODUCTNAME;, enter the command <link linkend="command-bye">BYE</link> or <link linkend="menu-file-exit">File-Exit</link>.
</para>

<para>
If you invoke a procedure that has not been defined, &PRODUCTNAME; first looks for a file in the current directory named <filename>proc.lgo</filename> where "proc" is the procedure name in lower case letters.
If such a file exists, &PRODUCTNAME; loads that file.
If the missing procedure is still undefined, or if there is no such file, &PRODUCTNAME; then looks in the library directory for a file named <filename>proc</filename> (without the ".lgo" extension) and, if it exists, loads it.
If neither file contains a definition for the procedure, then &PRODUCTNAME; signals an error.
</para>

<para>
Many of &PRODUCTNAME;'s built-in procedures are included in the default library, so if you use a different library you may want to include some or all of the default library in it.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
