<section id="command-step">
<title>STEP</title>
<indexterm><primary>STEP</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>STEP</command> <parameter>contentslist</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Marks the items in the contents list for stepping.
</para>

<para>
Whenever a stepped procedure is invoked, each instruction line in the procedure body is displayed in a dialog box before being executed and &PRODUCTNAME; waits for the user to press the OK button before continuing.
The line is truncated according to the current values of <link linkend="command-printwidthlimit">PRINTWIDTHLIMIT</link> and <link linkend="command-printdepthlimit">PRINTDEPTHLIMIT</link>.
</para>

<para>
Whenever a stepped variable is "shadowed", a message to this effect is printed to the commander's Output/Command-Recall box.
A variable is shadowed whenever a variable of the same name is created with the <link linkend="command-local">LOCAL</link> command or when a procedure is invoked that has an input with the same name.
If the variable was shadowed by LOCAL, then the instruction line that caused the shadowing is printed after the message.
This instruction line is truncated according to the current values of <link linkend="command-printwidthlimit">PRINTWIDTHLIMIT</link> and <link linkend="command-printdepthlimit">PRINTDEPTHLIMIT</link>.
</para>

<para>
STEP has no effect on property lists.
</para>

<para>
STEP does not throw an error if it is asked to step a procedure or variable that is not in the workspace, but doing so has no effect.
STEP also does not throw an error if asked to step a primitive, but this also has no effect.
</para>

<para>
See the <link linkend="workspace-queries">Workspace Queries</link> section for an explanation of the <parameter>contentslist</parameter> input.
</para>

<para>
You can step all procedures and variables with the <link linkend="commander-step">Step Button</link>.
</para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>
<programlisting><userinput>TO MYPROGRAM
  FORWARD 10
  RIGHT   90
  FORWARD 20
  LEFT    90
END

STEP "MYPROGRAM
MYPROGRAM</userinput>
<replaceable>Each line of MYPROGRAM is displayed and waits for OK to continue to next line.</replaceable>
<userinput>UNSTEP "MYPROGRAM
MYPROGRAM</userinput>
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry><term>See Also</term>
<listitem><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="command-unstep">UNSTEP</link></member>
<member><link linkend="workspace-queries">Workspace Queries</link></member>
</simplelist></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</section>
