<chapter id="editor">
    <title>Editor</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Editor</primary></indexterm>

    <para>When you exit the editor, &PRODUCTNAME; loads the revised definitions and modifies the workspace accordingly.
Multiple edit sessions are supported, but be careful of having multiple edit sessions that include the same definition.
The final editor that is exited (and saved) takes precedence.
Also realize if you delete procedures, property lists, or names while in the editor, then they are erased (see <link linkend="command-erase">ERASE</link>) from the workspace at the time of exiting (and saving) the edit session you deleted them from.
</para>

    <section id="editor-menu">
      <title>Editor Menu</title>

      <section id="editor-menu-file">
        <title>File Menu</title>

         <section id="editor-menu-file-saveandexit">
          <title>File - Save and Exit</title>
          <para>Saves the contents of the editor to the workspace and exits the editor.
When you exit the editor, &PRODUCTNAME; loads the revised definitions and modifies the workspace accordingly.
Multiple edit sessions are supported, but be careful not to have multiple edit sessions that include the definition of the same procedure, property, or variable.
The final editor that is exited (and saved) takes precedence.
Also realize if you delete procedures, property lists, or names while in the editor, then they are erased (see <link linkend="command-erase">ERASE</link>) from the workspace at the time of exiting (and saving) the edit session you deleted them from.
See also <link linkend="editor-errors">Edit Errors</link>.
</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-file-savetoworkspace">
          <title>File - Save to Workspace</title>
          <para>Saves the contents of the editor to the &GENERICNAME; workspace without exiting.
This is only available in <link linkend="commandline-e">expert mode</link>.
</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-file-print">
          <title>File - Print...</title>
          <para>Prints the contents of the editor.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-file-exit">
          <title>File - Exit</title>
          <para>Prompts you whether to save the changes to the &GENERICNAME; workspace and then exits the editor.
          Select this option if you want to discard your changes.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="editor-menu-edit">
        <title>Edit Menu</title>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-undo">
          <title>Edit - Undo</title>
          <para>Undoes the previous editor operation.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-redo">
          <title>Edit - Redo</title>
          <para>Reverts the previous undo operation.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-cut">
          <title>Edit - Cut</title>
          <para>Copies the selected text to the clipboard and deletes it.
          See also <link linkend="editor-clipboard">Editing with the Clipboard</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-copy">
          <title>Edit - Copy</title>
          <para>Copies the selected text to the clipboard.
          See also <link linkend="editor-clipboard">Editing with the Clipboard</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-paste">
          <title>Edit - Paste</title>
          <para>Pastes the text in the clipboard to the cursor position.
If text is selected it is replaced with the pasted text.
See also <link linkend="editor-clipboard">Editing with the Clipboard</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-delete">
          <title>Edit - Delete</title>
          <para>Deletes the selected text.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-clearall">
          <title>Edit - Clear All</title>
          <para>Deletes all text in the editor.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-edit-selectall">
          <title>Edit - Select All</title>
          <para>Selects all text in the editor.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="editor-menu-search">
        <title>Search Menu</title>

        <section id="editor-menu-search-find">
          <title>Search - Find</title>
          <para>Displays a dialog box that allows you to search for text within the editor.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-search-replace">
          <title>Search - Replace</title>
          <para>Displays a dialog box that allows you to search for text within the editor and replace it with other text.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-search-next">
          <title>Search - Next</title>
          <para>Repeats the previous Search - Find operation.</para>
        </section>

      </section>


      <section id="editor-menu-set">
        <title>Set Menu</title>

        <section id="editor-menu-set-font">
          <title>Set - Font</title>
          <para>You can change the editor's font by going to the Font Menu of the editor and selecting the desired font.
The new font affects the entire Editor not just selected Text.
The chosen font remains selected even after &PRODUCTNAME; has been restarted.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="editor-menu-test">
        <title>Test Menu</title>

        <section id="editor-menu-testbang">
          <title>Run Selection</title>
          <para>You can test your code by selecting a section of code and clicking on Run Selection in the menu.
This sends each selected line to the commander for execution.
Keep in mind that if you select code that has variables or other context that they must be defined in the selection or already defined in the workspace.
Using this feature is as if you typed in that selection into the commander.
</para>
        </section>

      </section>


      <section id="editor-menu-help">
        <title>Help Menu</title>

        <section id="editor-menu-help-index">
          <title>Help - Index</title>
          <para>Brings you to the help on &PRODUCTNAME;.  See also <link linkend="editor-context-help">Context Sensitive Help</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-help-editor">
          <title>Help - Editor</title>
          <para>Brings you to the help on &PRODUCTNAME;'s editor.  See also <link linkend="editor-context-help">Context Sensitive Help</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="editor-menu-help-topicsearch">
          <title>Help - Topic Search</title>
          <para>Searches for the topic selected by the mouse in the online help.  See also <link linkend="editor-context-help">Context Sensitive Help</link>.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="editor-errors">
      <title>Editor Errors</title>

      <para>If an error occurs when &GENERICNAME; "loads" your edit, it prompts you to fix the error in the Editor.
This situation commonly occurs when a continuation "~" is missing within a list or missing a matching "]".
When the editor is reopened, &PRODUCTNAME; places the cursor at the start of the definition that has the error.
When this occurs make sure to check the commander window for a hint of what the problem was when loading.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="editor-clipboard">
      <title>Editing with the Clipboard</title>
<para>
The Editor and many controls support the clipboard.
The clipboard is where most Windows application store data during cut and paste operations.
This means that when you cut text from an application, such as Notepad, it can be pasted into &GENERICNAME;'s Editor (the reverse is also true).
Even Help supports the clipboard.
This means you can copy examples in this document directly to the editor (see <link linkend="command-help">HELP</link> command).</para>

<para>
The <link linkend="commander-input">Input Box</link> also supports the clipboard.
Only one line of text is supported between the Input Box and the clipboard.
You can either use the context-sensitive popup menu or keyboard shortcuts for the desired actions (Cut <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>X</keycap></keycombo>, Copy <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>, Paste <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>).
</para>

<para>
The <link linkend="commander-history">Output/Command-Recall</link> also supports the clipboard.
This means you can turn code you entered in the commander into procedure by copying the Commander Output to the clipboard and pasting it into the editor.
Or take text output you generated and paste it into another application.
</para>
    </section>

    <section id="editor-context-help">
      <title>Context Sensitive Help</title>
      <para>&PRODUCTNAME;'s <link linkend="editor">Editor</link>, <link linkend="commander-input">Input Box</link> and <link linkend="commander-history">Output/Command-Recall</link> all support context sensitive Help.
If you select a keyword (such as FORWARD) in these places (double-click works best in the editor) you can ask &PRODUCTNAME; to look up the keyword without going through the Help Menu followed by a Search and so on.
You simply ask by clicking the right button on the mouse (or by hitting the <keycap>F1</keycap> key), abbreviations are also supported.
See also <link linkend="editor-clipboard">Editing with the Clipboard</link> to bring information back from the help system (like example code) for you to work with.</para>
    </section>


</chapter>
