<chapter id="main-menu">
   <title>Main Menu</title>
   <para>The main menu is where you do high-level tasks in &PRODUCTNAME;, such as loading a &GENERICNAME; program, loading an image, setting up a printer, or even reading this help file.</para>

      <section id="menu-file">
        <title>File Menu</title>
        <para>The File menu includes options that enable you to operate on &GENERICNAME; procedure files.
Note that, as a side effect, any selection in this menu that has a directory in its dialog box effectively changes the current working directory to that directory.</para>

        <section id="menu-file-new">
          <title>File - New</title>
          <para>This <link linkend="command-erase">ERASE</link>s all procedures, variables, and property lists in the workspace.
It's like starting with a "new" session.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-load">
          <title>File - Load...</title>
          <para>This loads procedures from disk into memory so that they can be executed or edited.
See also the <link linkend="command-load">LOAD</link> command.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-open">
          <title>File - Open...</title>
          <para>This erases all procedures in the workspace, then loads procedures from disk into memory.
This is equivalent to <link linkend="menu-file-new">File - New</link> followed by <link linkend="menu-file-load">File - Load</link>.
It exists to emphasize the difference between File - Load (which is modeled after the <link linkend="command-load">LOAD</link> command) and the way File - Open behaves in most Windows applications.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-save">
          <title>File - Save</title>
          <para>This saves everything that is loaded in memory onto the disk.
See also the <link linkend="command-save">SAVE</link> command.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-saveas">
          <title>File - Save As...</title>
          <para>This is the same as <link linkend="menu-file-save">File - Save</link>, except that it prompts you for a file name.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-setasscreensaver">
          <title>File - Set As Screen Saver</title>
          <para>This saves the current workspace to a file, configures the &PRODUCTNAME; screen saver to load this file, and sets the &PRODUCTNAME; screen saver as the active screen saver.  If the &PRODUCTNAME; screen saver is not installed, then this option is disabled.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-edit">
          <title>File - Edit...</title>
          <para>This is how you edit procedures that have already been loaded (or developed) in memory.
          This menu option prompts you to select which existing procedures you want to edit.
          You can also enter a new one.
See also the <link linkend="command-edit">EDIT</link> command.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-erase">
          <title>File - Erase...</title>
          <para>This is how you erase procedures that have already been loaded (or developed) in memory.
          This menu option prompts you to select which existing procedures you want to erase.
See also the <link linkend="command-erase">ERASE</link> command.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-file-exit">
          <title>File - Exit</title>
          <para>This is how you exit &PRODUCTNAME;.
See also the <link linkend="command-bye">BYE</link> command.</para>
        </section>

      </section>


      <section id="menu-bitmap">
        <title>Bitmap Menu</title>
        <para>The Bitmap menu includes options that operate on bitmap files.</para>

        <section id="menu-bitmap-new">
          <title>Bitmap - New</title>
          <para>This clears the work done on the screen and creates a new environment to save things in.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-bitmap-load">
          <title>Bitmap - Load...</title>
          <para>This reads an image that is stored on your file system.
You can load images in either the Microsoft Windows Bitmap (BMP) format or the Graphical Interlace Format (GIF) format.
Also see the <link linkend="command-bitload">BITLOAD</link> command.</para>

          <para>See also the section on <link linkend="using-color">using color</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-bitmap-save">
          <title>Bitmap - Save...</title>
          <para>This saves the picture that you're working so that you can use it with other applications or continue to work on it later.
You can save pictures as either a Microsoft Windows Bitmap (BMP) or a Graphical Interlace Format (GIF).
Remember, if your image was generated with a &GENERICNAME; program you really don't need to save it as an image unless you want to use the image in another application such as Microsoft Paint or as a wallpaper.
Also see the <link linkend="command-bitsave">BITSAVE</link> command.</para>

          <para>See also the <link linkend="command-setactivearea">SETACTIVEAREA</link> command.</para>
        </section>


        <section id="menu-bitmap-saveas">
          <title>Bitmap - Save As...</title>
          <para>This is similar to the Bitmap - Save menu option, but it prompts you for a new file name.</para>
        </section>


        <section id="menu-bitmap-print">
          <title>Bitmap - Print...</title>
          <para>This prints the active area on the screen to the printer.</para>
        </section>


        <section id="menu-bitmap-printersetup">
          <title>Bitmap - Printer Setup...</title>
          <para>This brings up a dialog box to configure the default printer.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-bitmap-activearea">
          <title>Bitmap - Active Area...</title>
          <para>This allows you to select which portion of the screen will be printed or saved.
The primary purpose of this option is performance and space.
You no longer need to wait for the software to build a full image.
It takes less time and less memory to print and disk space to save a partial image.
As a side effect you can adjust where your image ends up on the page by selecting different extents.
You may at anytime click on reset to put the extents back to the full image.
&PRODUCTNAME; remembers what you set them to even after you exit.</para>

          <para>This menu option also allows you to set how many "turtle steps" are mapped to an inch on your printout.
The default is 125 turtle steps per inch of paper.
Since &PRODUCTNAME;'s drawing surface defaults to 1000 x 1000 turtle steps, that equates to about 8 x 8 inches (1000/125 x 1000/125).
You may increase this number to take advantage of higher resolution printers but your image will become smaller.
You can compensate for this by increasing your drawing surface (and your drawing's size).</para>

          <para>You can also set the active area with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setactivearea">SETACTIVEAREA</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; operation <link linkend="command-activearea">ACTIVEAREA</link>.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="menu-set">
        <title>Set Menu</title>
        <para>The Set menu allows you to change some of the characteristics of how &PRODUCTNAME; behaves when drawing.</para>

        <section id="menu-set-pensize">
          <title>Set - Pen Size...</title>
          <para>This allows you to set the pen size with which the turtle draws.
You can also set the pen size with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setpensize">SETPENSIZE</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-pensize">PENSIZE</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-set-labelfont">
          <title>Set - Label Font...</title>
          <para>This allows you to set the font with which the <link linkend="command-label">LABEL</link> command writes.
You can also set the font with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setlabelfont">SETLABELFONT</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-labelfont">LABELFONT</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-set-commanderfont">
          <title>Set - Commander Font...</title>
          <para>This allows you to choose the font that is used by the <link linkend="commander">Commander</link>.
The chosen font remains selected even after &PRODUCTNAME; has been restarted.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-set-pencolor">
          <title>Set - Pen Color...</title>
          <para>This allows you to set the pen color.
You can also set the pen color with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setpencolor">SETPENCOLOR</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-pencolor">PENCOLOR</link>.</para>
        </section>


        <section id="menu-set-floodcolor">
          <title>Set - Flood Color...</title>
          <para>This allows you to set the flood color with which the turtle <link linkend="command-fill">FILL</link>s.
You can also set the flood color with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setfloodcolor">SETFLOODCOLOR</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-floodcolor">FLOODCOLOR</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-set-screencolor">
          <title>Set - Screen Color...</title>
          <para>This allows you to set the screen color.
You can also set the screen color with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-setscreencolor">SETSCREENCOLOR</link> and get it with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-screencolor">SCREENCOLOR</link>.</para>
        </section>

      </section>


      <section id="menu-zoom">
        <title>Zoom Menu</title>
        <para>The Zoom menu allows you set the zoom factor.
You can also set the zoom factor with the &GENERICNAME; command <link linkend="command-zoom">ZOOM</link>.</para>

        <section id="menu-zoom-in">
          <title>Zoom - In</title>
          <para>This menu option doubles the current zoom factor.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-zoom-out">
          <title>Zoom - Out</title>
          <para>This menu option halves the current zoom factor.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-zoom-normal">
          <title>Zoom - Normal</title>
          <para>This menu option restores the zoom factor to 1.0 (no zooming).</para>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="menu-help">
        <title>Help Menu</title>
        <para>The Help menu allows you to learn more about &PRODUCTNAME;.
For more information, select the Help menu command name.
Also see the <link linkend="command-help">HELP</link> command.</para>

        <section id="menu-help-index">
          <title>Help - Index</title>
          <para>This displays the manual for &PRODUCTNAME; and presents you with a searchable index.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-help-tutorial">
          <title>Help - Tutorial</title>
          <para>This brings you to the <link linkend="tutorial">tutorial</link> section in the help menu.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-help-demo">
          <title>Help - Demo</title>
          <para>This runs the DEMO program from the &GENERICNAME; library.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-help-example">
          <title>Help - Examples</title>
          <para>This brings you to an HTML page that describes each example program that comes with &PRODUCTNAME;.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-help-releasenotes">
          <title>Help - Release Notes</title>
          <para>This displays the release notes for this version of &PRODUCTNAME;.</para>
        </section>


        <section id="menu-help-aboutfmslogo">
          <title>Help - About &PRODUCTNAME;</title>
          <para>This displays the copyright and version information for &PRODUCTNAME;.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="menu-help-aboutms">
          <title>Help - About MS</title>
          <para>This displays information on Multiple Sclerosis.</para>
        </section>

      </section>

</chapter>
